People live to save themselves
Good night, Kosuke.
おやすみ　幸介
Good night, Katsumi.
おやすみ　克巳
Good night, Yu.
おやすみ　優
Good night, Shinji.
おやすみ　真嗣
おやすみ　咲楽
Good night, Sakura.
Rest in peace.
静かに眠ってくれ
I'll be off.
行ってくる
Thank you for coming here today.
本日はご足労いただき有り難う御座います
Again, this is an unofficial meeting.
繰り返しますが　これは非公式の会合です
Thank you for inviting me here today.
今日はお招きありがとう
How does it feel to be
back in your main job?
本職に戻ってからの調子はどうかな
Please don't torture our junior staff,
うちの若いもんをあんまり虐めんでいただきたいですな
ポートマフィアの親分さん
Port Mafia's boss-man.
My Elise-chan wants ice cream.
うちのエリスちゃんがアイスクリームを所望でねぇ
政府御用達のいい店でもないかねぇ　種田長官
Are there any ice cream shops that
government workers would recommend,
Chief Taneda?
That is a heartwarming topic.
そりゃあ微笑ましい話ですな
うちの官僚達にも土産を持ち帰ってやらんと
I need to bring back gifts
for our officials, as well.
I bet they would be more than happy
お宅の首級なんか
to see your head on a platter.
喜ばれるやろなぁ
早速ですが　本題に入らせていただきます
If we may, let us proceed
right to the agenda.
The Gifted Special Operations
Division has two
異能特務課拠り　ポートマフィア鷗外殿への要求は二点
requests for Ougai-dono of the Port Mafia.
First, the Port Mafia will divest themselves
先ず私　坂口安吾について一切の関知をせず　危害を加えぬこと
of any interest in myself, Sakaguchi Ango,
and will not harm my person.
Second, the Port Mafia will dispose of Mimic,
もう一つは　日本に不法入国した異能犯罪組織ミミックを壊滅させること
the gifted criminal organization
that has illegally entered Japan.
一つ目に関しては問題ないよ
I have no qualms with the first request.
But I hesitate to agree to the second.
でも二つ目は確約しかねるなー
とにかく怖い連中だからね
After all, they are a terrifying bunch...
まあ　条件にも拠るがね
Well, it'd depend on the conditions.
Odasaku.
織田作
I know what you're thinking.
君が何を考えているかわかるよ
けどやめるんだ
But don't do it.
そんなことをしても
Even if you do it...
そんなことをしても　子ども達は戻ってこない
Even if I do it, it won't
bring the kids back.
They still have numbers.
連中はまだ余力を残してる
And they are at...
そして奴らの居場所は…
連中の居場所ならもうわかってる
I know where they are.
I got an invitation, see.
招待状が来たからな
聞いてくれ
Listen to me.
先程首領が秘密の会合に出席したらしい
The Boss just attended a secret meeting.
It was with the Gifted Special Ops Division.
相手は異能特務課
There's something more than this going on.
この一件にはまだ何か裏がある
There's nothing more going on, Dazai.
何かなどないよ　太宰
もう凡て終わった
It's all over for me.
Odasaku.
織田作
おかしな云い方を許してほしい
Forgive me for putting it this
way, but please hear me out.
でも聞いてくれ　何かに頼るんだ
You need to rely on something.
It can be anything.
何でもいい
You should wait and see what
happens next, whatever that is!
この後に起こる何かに期待するんだ
それはきっとある筈なんだ
It will happen.
Hey, Odasaku.
ねぇ　織田作
私が何故ポートマフィアに入ったかわかるかい
Do you know why I joined the Port Mafia?
そこに何かあると期待したからだよ
I was hoping there'd be
something in it for me.
If you place yourself somewhere
close to raw emotions,
暴力や死　本能や欲望
where you're exposed to violence
and death, instinct and desire,
そういったむき出しの感情に近い処にいれば
you can brush against man's true nature.
人間の本質に触れることができる
I thought that way I could...
そうすれば何か…
I could find a reason to live somehow.
何か生きる理由が見つかると思ったんだ
I wanted to become a writer.
俺は小説家になりたかった
再び人を殺したら　その資格がなくなると思った
I thought I'd lose my right
to do that if I killed again.
That's why I stopped killing.
だから殺しをやめた
Odasaku.
織田作
だがそれも終わりだ
But all that's come to a close.
Don't go!
行くな　織田作
Odasaku!
I only want one thing.
俺の望みは一つだけだ
織田作
Odasaku!
Ow...
いたたたた
君　何をするんだい
Hey!
What do you think you're doing?
ちゃんと前を見て歩かなきゃ駄目じゃないか
You should look where you're going!
せっかく社長に貰った名探偵道具が…
You almost ruined the famous detective
tools the president gave me.
探偵？
Detective?
Not just any detective!
探偵じゃない　名探偵
I'm a great detective!
Soon, my name will be known in every
household throughout Japan.
じきに日本中が僕の名前を知ることになる
I am the best detective the world
has ever known, Edogawa Rampo.
僕こそは世界最高の名探偵　江戸川乱…
Sorry I asked.
すまなかった
Hey, wait!
ちょっと待ったー
Once you see my ability,
僕の能力を見れば　そんな無下な態度は取れなくなるよ
you will not be so rude to me!
疑うなら見せてあげよう
If you doubt me, I'll show you.
Let's see...
どれどれ
I'm not trying to be mean here,
君　悪いことは云わない
but you should not go
to where you're headed.
目的地に行くのはやめたほうがいい
You should reconsider.
考え直すべきだ
If you go,
行ったら君
you'll die.
死ぬよ
Yeah.
ああ
I know.
知っている
Do you want me to finish it?
とどめは要るか
Yeah...
ああ　頼む
Please.
何か云い残すことはあるか
Any last words?
Thank you...
ありがとう　戦ってくれて
for fighting us...
Our leader... is up ahead...
司令官はこの先だ
Please save him, too...
彼も救ってやってくれ　この地獄から
from this hell..
Yeah.
ああ　わかってる
I know.
おや　太宰君
Oh? Dazai-kun.
君のほうから来るとは珍しいな
How rare of you to come visit.
Boss.
首領　織田作を救援する為の異能力者部隊編成の許可をいただきたい
I'd like to request permission to organize
a gifted squad to save Odasaku.
Very well.
いいよ　許可しよう
Permission granted.
だが　理由を教えてもらえるかな
But first, why?
今織田作はミミック本拠地で単身に拠る威力偵察を行っています
Odasaku is currently doing reconnaissance
in force by himself at Mimic headquarters.
このままでは貴重な異能力者である織田作が死にます
If we do nothing, he will die, and we
will lose a valuable gifted agent.
君の思考は理解できる
I understand your reasoning.
だが織田君は恐らく誰かの救援など望んではいないだろう
But I doubt Oda-kun wants
to be saved by anyone.
それについてはどう思うね
What do you think about that?
Dazai-kun, the leader of an organization
is at the pinnacle of that organization
太宰君　首領というのはね
組織の頂点であると同時に組織の奴隷だ
and, at the same time, he is its slave.
組織存続の為なら　どんな非道も喜んで行わなければならない
The leader must be more than willing
to commit any atrocity in order to
ensure the organization's survival.
That envelope...
その封筒は…
I see. I get it now.
そうか　そういうことか
Where are you going?
どこへ行くのかな
To Odasaku.
織田作の処へ
"It remains only a single seed."
一粒の麦　もし地に落ちて死なずば　ただ一つにてあらん
"Unless a kernel of wheat falls
to the ground and dies,"
"it remains only a single seed."
死なば…
"But if it dies..."
死なば　多くの実を結ぶべし
"But if it dies, it produces many seeds."
John 12:24.
『ヨハネ伝』第十二章二十四節
You're more well-read than
you look, Sakunosuke.
見かけに拠らず博識だな　作之助
I apologize for the children.
子ども達には申し訳ないことをした
But it seems to have been worth it.
だがその価値はあったようだ
Your eyes are the same as mine now.
貴君の目は乃公と同じだ
Like my subordinates and I,
乃公や部下と同じ　生存の階段から降りた目だ
you look like someone who has left
the stairway of continued existence.
Welcome, Sakunosuke, to our world!
ようこそ作之助　俺達の世界へ
未来の読み合いでは埒が明かないな
We don't seem to make any progress
by just reading our own futures.
It seems not.
そのようだ
ならば　未来予測など使わずにやり合うだけだ
Then we just have to duel without
using our predictive abilities.
Indeed.
そうだな　作之助
You're right, Sakunosuke.
You are the best.
矢張りお前は最高だ
We have not ended the debate, Dazai-kun.
まだ議論が途中だよ　太宰君
I've been thinking a long time
ずっと考えていました
about the Port Mafia, Mimic, and
the black special ops group...
ポートマフィアとミミックと黒の特殊部隊
or, rather, in this case, the Gifted
Special Operations Division...
いや　この場合は異能特務課と云うべきですね
and who's the one controlling the
conflict between the three groups.
この三組織を巡る対立は誰が操っていたのか
This bold and intricate design
was your handiwork, Boss.
この大胆かつ精緻な絵を描いたのは　首領　あなただ
That black envelope
contains that much value.
その黒い封筒にはそれだけの価値がある
No matter how powerful the
Port Mafia may become,
ポートマフィアがどれほど強大な力を持っていようとも
we exist in constant fear
政府機関である異能特務課の機嫌を損ね
of displeasing the Gifted Special
Operations Division and being oppressed.
弾圧される可能性に常に怯えていなければならない
That is why, as the price
for crushing Mimic,
だからあなたはミミックを潰す対価として
you negotiated for the
issuance of this permit.
この証書を発行させる取引を持ちかけた
This permit, which allows us to
operate a gifted organization...
異能組織として活動を許可するこの証書
Gifted
Business
Permit
the Gifted Business Permit.
異能開業許可証を
最高だ　作之助
You're perfect, Sakunosuke.
Today, I'm with you all the way.
今日はとことん付き合ってやる
What?
なんだ
これが安吾の云っていた…
Is this what Ango was talking about?
異能力の特異点
The singularity of the ability?!
これが乃公の求めた世界だ
This is the world I've sought.
何故求めた
Why did you want it?
お前は何故殺しをやめた
Why did you stop killing?
俺は小説家になりたかった
I wanted to become a writer.
A man told me that's what I should do.
ある人に云われたんだ　そうすべきだと
He gave me a book.
その人は本をくれた
俺がずっと探していた小説の下巻だ
It was the last volume of a novel I've
been seeking for a very long time.
Before I read it, he told me
that it's a terrible book.
読む前に　非道い本だと釘を刺された
And how was it?
それで　どうだった
It was a wonderful book.
その本は…
とても素晴らしい本だった
You are the one who helped them
enter the country illegally.
首領　彼らの密入国を裏で手助けしたのはあなただ
You invited the enemy
organization to Yokohama
あなたは異能特務課を焦らせ　重い腰を上げさせる為に
to incite the Gifted Special Operations
Division into finally taking action.
わざと敵対組織を横浜に招いた
Yes.
そう　そのおかげでこうして異能開業許可証は手に入り
Thanks to that, we now have
the Gifted Business Permit.
The government has, for all practical
purposes, ratified our illegal activities.
事実上　政府から非合法活動は認可され
厄介な乱暴者は織田君が命を賭して排除してくれている
The troublesome aggressors will be taken
care of by Oda-kun with his life.
大金星だよ
This is a glorious victory for us.
And yet... Why are you so angry?
なのに君は何をそんなに怒っているのかね
You're the one who let Mimic know about
the orphans under Odasaku's care.
織田作が養っていた孤児達の存在をミミックに密告したのはあなただ
You did it so you could counter
Mimic's leader with Odasaku,
織田作を　ミミックの指揮官に唯一抗しうる異能力者として
the only gifted agent
who could be his match.
敵にぶつける為に
Dazai-kun.
太宰君
You need to stay here.
君はここに居なさい
それとも
Or is there a logical reason
why you should go to him?
彼の許に行く合理的な理由でもあるのかね
There are two things I
wish to say to you, Boss.
云いたいことが二つあります　首領
First, you will not shoot me.
一つ　あなたは私を撃たない
Nor will you have your
subordinates shoot me.
部下に撃たせることもしない
What makes you think that?
どうしてそう思うね
Because you have nothing to gain from it.
利益がないからです
I believe you also have nothing to
gain by defying me and going to him.
君にも私の制止を振り切って　彼の許に行く利益などないと思うが
As for the second thing, Boss.
それが二つ目です　首領
There may be nothing to gain by my actions,
確かに利益はありません
but there is one reason why I will still go.
私が行く理由は一つです
It's because he is a friend.
彼が友達だからですよ
The last book in the series was wonderful,
その下巻は素晴らしい本だったが　一つだけ欠点があった
but there was one flaw.
Several pages had been cut out
and removed toward the end.
最後に近い数頁が切り取られていたんだ
Then you write it.
ならばお前が書け
Right before the removed
section, there was this line:
その下巻の切り取られたシーンの直前にこういう台詞があった
"People live to save themselves."
"You will understand that at the
moment of your own death."
People live to save themselves. You will understand
that at the moment of your own death.
人は自分を救済する為に生きている
死ぬ間際にそれがわかるだろう
Now, I think that the man who gave me the
book knew I was a hired killer.
今になって思う
本をくれたあの男は俺を殺し屋だと知っていたのではないか
He knew, and spoke to me so
that I would stop killing.
知っていて　殺しをやめさせる為に声をかけたのではないか
He told me his name when we first met.
最初に会った時　その男は俺に名乗った
I'd forgotten that name
for a very long time,
ずっと忘れていたが　つい最近になって彼の名を思い出した
but I finally remembered
what it was recently.
Who are you?
あなたは誰なんです
Me?
儂か
My name is Natsume Souseki.
儂の名は夏目漱石
That's right.
そう　その小説にあった著者と　同じ名前だ
He had the same name as
the author of the story.
I was a hero.
乃公は英雄だった
祖国を守ることが自分の天命だと信じて戦った
I fought believing it was my god-given
destiny to protect my homeland.
先の大戦で俺達は僅か四十名の部隊で
In the last great war,
my squad of forty defeated six hundred
enemies who were holed up in a fortress.
砦に籠る六百人の敵を打ち倒した
だがそれは味方本部の計略だった
But that was a setup by
our allied headquarters.
At the time, our country was
already entering peace talks.
既にその時　本国では和平交渉が行われており
和平後の敵交通網を奪取という
We were used to commit an unjust
act for the military staff,
軍幕僚幹部の不義に利用されたのだ
by seizing an enemy transportation
network after peace was achieved.
Of course, our actions
were deemed a war crime.
当然俺達の行動は戦争犯罪になった
Our comrades in arms became our enemies
now that we were labeled rebels.
同胞が反逆者である俺達の相手となる
部隊の中には自殺する者もいた
Some in my unit took their own lives.
だが
But there were those who survived.
死なない者もいた
We lost our homeland and our honor.
俺達は祖国を失い　誇りを失った
We became ghosts wandering a wasteland
in search of enemies to fight.
そしてただ敵を求め　戦い続ける　荒野の死霊となった
生き方を変えることは本当にできなかったのか
Are you sure you couldn't
change your way of life?
I swore to my men that
I would die a soldier.
乃公は軍人として死ぬと仲間に誓った
それ以外になるのは不可能だ
I cannot become anything else.
いや　あるいはできたのかもしれない
No... perhaps I could have.
生き方を曲げ　軍人ではない何かになることは可能だったのかもしれない
I may have been able to reshape my way of life
and become someone who wasn't a soldier.
Just like how you stopped killing.
お前が殺しをやめたように
一つ心残りがある
I have one regret.
I did not say farewell to my friend.
友にさよならを云っていない
To the man who was my only friend
in this world I live in.
この世界で　ただの友人でいてくれた男だ
He seemed to have tired of the world
この世界に退屈し　ずっと死を待っているように見えた
and was waiting for death.
その男は乃公と同じように死を求めていたのか
Was he in search of death like me?
No.
いいや
I think it's different.
違うと思う
作之助
Sakunosuke.
Even your last shot was perfect.
最後まで　素晴らしい弾丸だ
Odasaku!
織田作
You're an idiot, Odasaku.
莫迦だよ　織田作
君は大莫迦だ
You're a complete idiot...
Yeah...
ああ
Why did you go along with what he wanted?
あんな奴に付き合うなんて
Dazai...
太宰
お前に云っておきたいことがある
There's something I want to say to you.
駄目だ　やめてくれ
No!
Don't!
まだ助かるかもしれない
You might still make it!
いや　きっと助かる
No, you will make it!
だからそんな風に…
So don't talk like—
聞け
Listen.
お前は云ったな
You told me that you might
find a reason to live
暴力と流血の世界にいれば　生きる理由が見つかるかもしれないと
if you lived in a world of
violence and bloodshed.
Yeah, I did.
ああ　云った
But who cares what I said now?
云ったがそんなこと今は
You won't find it.
見つからないよ
自分でもわかっている筈だ
You must know that already.
Whether you're on the side who kills people
人を殺す側だろうと　救う側だろうと
or the side who saves people,
お前の予測を超えるものは現れない
nothing beyond what you
would expect will appear.
Nothing in this world can fill
that lonely hole you have.
お前の孤独を埋めるものは　この世のどこにもない
You will wander the darkness for eternity.
お前は永遠に闇の中を彷徨う
Odasaku...
織田作
私はどうすればいい
What should I do?
Be on the side that saves people.
人を救う側になれ
どちらも同じなら　いい人間になれ
If both sides are the same,
become a good man.
弱者を救い　孤児を守れ
Save the weak, and protect the orphans.
正義も悪もお前には大差ないだろうが
Neither good nor evil means
much to you, I know...
but that'd make you at
least a little bit better.
そのほうが幾分か素敵だ
How do you know that for sure?
何故わかる
Of course I know.
わかるさ　誰よりもわかる
I know better than anyone.
俺はお前の友達だからな
Because... I am your friend.
I see.
わかった　そうしよう
I'll do that.
人は自分を救済する為に存在するか
People exist to save themselves, huh...
確かにその通りだ
How true...
Two Weeks Later
内務省の重鎮がこんな安酒場で独り手酌とは
I didn't think a heavyweight in
the Ministry of Internal Affairs
would be drinking alone
in a cheap bar like this.
寂しい限りですな　種田長官
How lonesome, Chief Taneda.
You are...
君は…
Now, now, now...
まあまあまあまあまあ
暫く行方を眩ませとったと噂で聞いたが
I heard rumors that you had
gone underground for a while.
転職先を探してましてね
I'm looking for a new job.
Do you know of any good positions?
どこかお勧めはありませんか
Do you wish to join the Gifted Special
Operations Division? If so...
特務課を希望かな　それなら…
I regretfully decline the offer.
そちらのほうは辞退しますよ
規則の多い職場は肌に合わなくてね
I don't do too well in a workplace
that has a lot of regulations.
Then what are you looking for?
では　何が希望かね
人助けができる処
Somewhere I can help people.
聞きたいことは山ほどあるが
I have a lot of questions for you, but...
君の経歴は汚れ過ぎとる
Your history is too sordid.
You'll have to go underground for at
least two years to get a blank slate.
洗う為には二年ほど地下に潜る必要があるぞ
But I suppose I may have a lead...
だがまあ　心当たりがないわけでもない
伺いましょう
Let's hear it.
異能力者を集めた武装組織だ
There is an armed organization
of gifted individuals.
They take on cases that are in a legal gray
zone and are untouchable by civil workers.
公僕には頼れぬ灰色の厄介事を引き受け　解決する
そこの社長は心ある男でな
The company president is a man of integrity.
君の希望に添うかもしれん
You may find him in alignment
with what you wish.
人を救う仕事ができますか
鏡花ちゃんの武装探偵社での初めての仕事
Can I do work that saves people?
Episode 16
Bungo Stray Dogs
それは書類を裁判所に届けるだけの簡単な仕事
And the story resumes,
four years later
…のはずだったんだけど
私が得意なのは色仕掛けで人気のない処に誘い込んでから
Next Time: Episode 17
Three Companies Conflict
ぐさりと刺す
それはもう忘れなさい
そんな鏡花ちゃんを追って現れるポートマフィアの追手
そして　さらにどんでもない敵が現れた
次回　文豪ストレイドッグス　第十七話
三社鼎立